Jack: So, what are the advantages and
disadvantages of functional, object
oriented and other coding types.
Leah: Let’s start by
looking at Functional coding
The Advantages of Functional coding are:
- It’s easy to debug [no side effects
or hidden inputs or outputs]
- Functions are easier to understand
because they do not affect any
variables outside of themself.
The Disadvantages of
Functional coding are:
- The type of function used can
reduce the readability of the code.
- Using recursive functions instead
of loops can take a while to learn.
Jack: Now let’s look at Object
Oriented Programming [OOP]
The Advantages of Object
Oriented Programming are:
- It is very mature and
professionally appreciated.
- It is also good for making
sophisticated software.
The Disadvantages of Object
Oriented Programming are:
- It involves a steep learning curve.
- Large programs end up with
slower operating speeds.
Leah: Let’s look at
some other coding types.
We have already looked at how
imperative and declarative coding
differs so let’s now look at the
advantages and disadvantages of
imperative and declarative coding.
Jack: Imperative coding is a relatively
simple concept, and it simplifies code
by reusing code sections, however,
there is a higher risk of making errors
when compared with declarative and
it can quickly become complicated.
This makes maintenance, optimisation,
and extension difficult.
Leah: Declarative coding is clearer than
imperative coding and we have mentioned
is easier to extend, but it can be more
difficult to understand for someone who
is not a domain specific specialist.
Jack: With Procedural coding it is easy
to track the flow of a program and it is
also easy to implement, debug and adapt.
However, it can be hard to write
and far abstracted from reality.
Leah: Logic programming is a rather high
level of coding which has good memory
management being fast and efficient.
But it can be difficult to apply in
more general contexts of computation.
Jack: Parallel processing is more
efficient than with sequential
programming as it reaches the outcome
quicker, but it can be more complex
to write, difficult to scale and has
potentially higher resource requirements.